<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Waste Land</title>
                <author>T.S. Eliot</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1922</date>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">
                <head>The Waste Land</head>
                <div type="section" n="1">
                    <head>The Burial of the Dead</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>April is the cruellest month, breeding</l>
                        <l>Lilacs out of the dead land, mixing</l>
                        <l>Memory and desire, stirring</l>
                        <l>Dull roots with spring rain.</l>
                        <l>Winter kept us warm, covering</l>
                        <l>Earth in forgetful snow, feeding</l>
                        <l>A little life with dried tubers.</l>
                        <l>Summer surprised us, coming over the Starnbergersee</l>
                        <l>With a shower of rain; we stopped in the colonnade,</l>
                        <l>And went on in sunlight, into the Hofgarten,</l>
                        <l>And drank coffee, and talked for an hour.</l>
                        <l>Bin gar keine Russin, stamm’ aus Litauen, echt deutsch.</l>
                        <l>And when we were children, staying at the archduke’s,</l>
                        <l>My cousin’s, he took me out on a sled,</l>
                        <l>And I was frightened. He said, Marie,</l>
                        <l>Marie, hold on tight. And down we went.</l>
                        <l>In the mountains, there you feel free.</l>
                        <l>I read, much of the night, and go south in the winter.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>What are the roots that clutch, what branches grow</l>
                        <l>Out of this stony rubbish? Son of man,</l>
                        <l>You cannot say, or guess, for you know only</l>
                        <l>A heap of broken images, where the sun beats,</l>
                        <l>And the dead tree gives no shelter, the cricket no relief,</l>
                        <l>And the dry stone no sound of water. Only</l>
                        <l>There is shadow under this red rock,</l>
                        <l>(Come in under the shadow of this red rock),</l>
                        <l>And I will show you something different from either</l>
                        <l>Your shadow at morning striding behind you</l>
                        <l>Or your shadow at evening rising to meet you;</l>
                        <l>I will show you fear in a handful of dust.</l>
                        <l>Frisch weht der Wind</l>
                        <l>Der Heimat zu</l>
                        <l>Mein Irisch Kind,</l>
                        <l>Wo weilest du?</l>
                        <l>‘You gave me hyacinths first a year ago;</l>
                        <l>‘They called me the hyacinth girl.’</l>
                        <l>—Yet when we came back, late, from the Hyacinth garden,</l>
                        <l>Your arms full, and your hair wet, I could not</l>
                        <l>Speak, and my eyes failed, I was neither</l>
                        <l>Living nor dead, and I knew nothing,</l>
                        <l>Looking into the heart of light, the silence.</l>
                        <l>Oed’ und leer das Meer.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Madame Sosostris, famous clairvoyante,</l>
                        <l>Had a bad cold, nevertheless</l>
                        <l>Is known to be the wisest woman in Europe,</l>
                        <l>With a wicked pack of cards. Here, said she,</l>
                        <l>Is your card, the drowned Phoenician Sailor,</l>
                        <l>(Those are pearls that were his eyes. Look!)</l>
                        <l>Here is Belladonna, the Lady of the Rocks,</l>
                        <l>The lady of situations.</l>
                        <l>Here is the man with three staves, and here the Wheel,</l>
                        <l>And here is the one-eyed merchant, and this card,</l>
                        <l>Which is blank, is something he carries on his back,</l>
                        <l>Which I am forbidden to see. I do not find</l>
                        <l>The Hanged Man. Fear death by water.</l>
                        <l>I see crowds of people, walking round in a ring.</l>
                        <l>Thank you. If you see dear Mrs. Equitone,</l>
                        <l>Tell her I bring the horoscope myself:</l>
                        <l>One must be so careful these days.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Unreal City,</l>
                        <l>Under the brown fog of a winter dawn,</l>
                        <l>A crowd flowed over London Bridge, so many,</l>
                        <l>I had not thought death had undone so many.</l>
                        <l>Sighs, short and infrequent, were exhaled,</l>
                        <l>And each man fixed his eyes before his feet.</l>
                        <l>Flowed up the hill and down King William Street,</l>
                        <l>To where Saint Mary Woolnoth kept the hours</l>
                        <l>With a dead sound on the final stroke of nine.</l>
                        <l>There I saw one I knew, and stopped him, crying: ‘Stetson!</l>
                        <l>‘You who were with me in the ships at Mylae!</l>
                        <l>‘That corpse you planted last year in your garden,</l>
                        <l>‘Has it begun to sprout? Will it bloom this year?</l>
                        <l>‘Or has the sudden frost disturbed its bed?</l>
                        <l>‘Oh keep the Dog far hence, that’s friend to men,</l>
                        <l>‘Or with his nails he’ll dig it up again!</l>
                        <l>‘You! hypocrite lecteur!—mon semblable,—mon frère!”</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="2">
                    <head>A Game of Chess</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>The Chair she sat in, like a burnished throne,</l>
                        <l>Glowed on the marble, where the glass</l>
                        <l>Held up by standards wrought with fruited vines</l>
                        <l>From which a golden Cupidon peeped out</l>
                        <l>(Another hid his eyes behind his wing)</l>
                        <l>Doubled the flames of sevenbranched candelabra</l>
                        <l>Reflecting light upon the table as</l>
                        <l>The glitter of her jewels rose to meet it,</l>
                        <l>From satin cases poured in rich profusion;</l>
                        <l>In vials of ivory and coloured glass</l>
                        <l>Unstoppered, lurked her strange synthetic perfumes,</l>
                        <l>Unguent, powdered, or liquid—troubled, confused</l>
                        <l>And drowned the sense in odours; stirred by the air</l>
                        <l>That freshened from the window, these ascended</l>
                        <l>In fattening the prolonged candle-flames,</l>
                        <l>Flung their smoke into the laquearia,</l>
                        <l>Stirring the pattern on the coffered ceiling.</l>
                        <l>Huge sea-wood fed with copper</l>
                        <l>Burned green and orange, framed by the coloured stone,</l>
                        <l>In which sad light a carvéd dolphin swam.</l>
                        <l>Above the antique mantel was displayed</l>
                        <l>As though a window gave upon the sylvan scene</l>
                        <l>The change of Philomel, by the barbarous king</l>
                        <l>So rudely forced; yet there the nightingale</l>
                        <l>Filled all the desert with inviolable voice</l>
                        <l>And still she cried, and still the world pursues,</l>
                        <l>‘Jug Jug’ to dirty ears.</l>
                        <l>And other withered stumps of time</l>
                        <l>Were told upon the walls; staring forms</l>
                        <l>Leaned out, leaning, hushing the room enclosed.</l>
                        <l>Footsteps shuffled on the stair.</l>
                        <l>Under the firelight, under the brush, her hair</l>
                        <l>Spread out in fiery points</l>
                        <l>Glowed into words, then would be savagely still.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘My nerves are bad tonight. Yes, bad. Stay with me.</l>
                        <l>Speak to me. Why do you never speak. Speak.</l>
                        <l>What are you thinking of? What thinking? What?</l>
                        <l>I never know what you are thinking. Think.’</l>
                        <l>I think we are in rats’ alley</l>
                        <l>Where the dead men lost their bones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘What is that noise?’</l>
                        <l>The wind under the door.</l>
                        <l>‘What is that noise now? What is the wind doing?’</l>
                        <l>Nothing again nothing.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘Do</l>
                        <l>You know nothing? Do you see nothing? Do you remember</l>
                        <l>Nothing?’</l>
                        <l>I remember</l>
                        <l>Those are pearls that were his eyes.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘Are you alive, or not? Is there nothing in your head?’</l>
                        <l>But</l>
                        <l>O O O O that Shakespeherian Rag—</l>
                        <l>It’s so elegant</l>
                        <l>So intelligent</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘What shall I do now? What shall I do?’</l>
                        <l>‘I shall rush out as I am, and walk the street</l>
                        <l>‘With my hair down, so. What shall we do tomorrow?</l>
                        <l>‘What shall we ever do?’</l>
                        <l>The hot water at ten.</l>
                        <l>And if it rains, a closed car at four.</l>
                        <l>And we shall play a game of chess,</l>
                        <l>Pressing lidless eyes and waiting for a knock upon the door.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>When Lil’s husband got demobbed, I said—</l>
                        <l>I didn’t mince my words, I said to her myself,</l>
                        <l>HURRY UP PLEASE ITS TIME</l>
                        <l>Now Albert’s coming back, make yourself a bit smart.</l>
                        <l>He’ll want to know what you done with that money he gave you</l>
                        <l>To get yourself some teeth. He did, I was there.</l>
                        <l>You have them all out, Lil, and get a nice set,</l>
                        <l>He said, I swear, I can’t bear to look at you.</l>
                        <l>And no more can’t I, I said, and think of poor Albert,</l>
                        <l>He’s been in the army four years, he wants a good time,</l>
                        <l>And if you don’t give it him, there’s others will, I said.</l>
                        <l>Oh is there, she said. Something o’ that, I said.</l>
                        <l>Then I’ll know who to thank, she said, and give me a straight look.</l>
                        <l>HURRY UP PLEASE ITS TIME</l>
                        <l>If you don’t like it you can get on with it, I said.</l>
                        <l>Others can pick and choose if you can’t.</l>
                        <l>But if Albert makes off, it won’t be for lack of telling.</l>
                        <l>You ought to be ashamed, I said, to look so antique.</l>
                        <l>(And her only thirty-one.)</l>
                        <l>I can’t help it, she said, pulling a long face,</l>
                        <l>It’s them pills I took, to bring it off, she said.</l>
                        <l>(She’s had five already, and nearly died of young George.)</l>
                        <l>The chemist said it would be all right, but I’ve never been the same.</l>
                        <l>You are a proper fool, I said.</l>
                        <l>Well, if Albert won’t leave you alone, there it is, I said,</l>
                        <l>What you get married for if you don’t want children?</l>
                        <l>HURRY UP PLEASE ITS TIME</l>
                        <l>Well, that Sunday Albert was home, they had a hot gammon,</l>
                        <l>And they asked me in to dinner, to get the beauty of it hot—</l>
                        <l>HURRY UP PLEASE ITS TIME</l>
                        <l>HURRY UP PLEASE ITS TIME</l>
                        <l>Goonight Bill. Goonight Lou. Goonight May. Goonight.</l>
                        <l>Ta ta. Goonight. Goonight.</l>
                        <l>Good night, ladies, good night, sweet ladies, good night, good night.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="3">
                    <head>The Fire Sermon</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>The river’s tent is broken: the last fingers of leaf</l>
                        <l>Clutch and sink into the wet bank. The wind</l>
                        <l>Crosses the brown land, unheard. The nymphs are departed.</l>
                        <l>Sweet Thames, run softly, till I end my song.</l>
                        <l>The river bears no empty bottles, sandwich papers,</l>
                        <l>Silk handkerchiefs, cardboard boxes, cigarette ends</l>
                        <l>Or other testimony of summer nights. The nymphs are departed.</l>
                        <l>And their friends, the loitering heirs of City directors;</l>
                        <l>Departed, have left no addresses.</l>
                        <l>By the waters of Leman I sat down and wept . . .</l>
                        <l>Sweet Thames, run softly till I end my song,</l>
                        <l>Sweet Thames, run softly, for I speak not loud or long.</l>
                        <l>But at my back in a cold blast I hear</l>
                        <l>The rattle of the bones, and chuckle spread from ear to ear.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>A rat crept softly through the vegetation</l>
                        <l>Dragging its slimy belly on the bank</l>
                        <l>While I was fishing in the dull canal</l>
                        <l>On a winter evening round behind the gashouse</l>
                        <l>Musing upon the king my brother’s wreck</l>
                        <l>And on the king my father’s death before him.</l>
                        <l>White bodies naked on the low damp ground</l>
                        <l>And bones cast in a little low dry garret,</l>
                        <l>Rattled by the rat’s foot only, year to year.</l>
                        <l>But at my back from time to time I hear</l>
                        <l>The sound of horns and motors, which shall bring</l>
                        <l>Sweeney to Mrs. Porter in the spring.</l>
                        <l>O the moon shone bright on Mrs. Porter</l>
                        <l>And on her daughter</l>
                        <l>They wash their feet in soda water</l>
                        <l>Et O ces voix d’enfants, chantant dans la coupole!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Twit twit twit</l>
                        <l>Jug jug jug jug jug jug</l>
                        <l>So rudely forc’d.</l>
                        <l>Tereu</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Unreal City</l>
                        <l>Under the brown fog of a winter noon</l>
                        <l>Mr. Eugenides, the Smyrna merchant</l>
                        <l>Unshaven, with a pocket full of currants</l>
                        <l>C.i.f. London: documents at sight,</l>
                        <l>Asked me in demotic French</l>
                        <l>To luncheon at the Cannon Street Hotel</l>
                        <l>Followed by a weekend at the Metropole.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>At the violet hour, when the eyes and back</l>
                        <l>Turn upward from the desk, when the human engine waits</l>
                        <l>Like a taxi throbbing waiting,</l>
                        <l>I Tiresias, though blind, throbbing between two lives,</l>
                        <l>Old man with wrinkled female breasts, can see</l>
                        <l>At the violet hour, the evening hour that strives</l>
                        <l>Homeward, and brings the sailor home from sea,</l>
                        <l>The typist home at teatime, clears her breakfast, lights</l>
                        <l>Her stove, and lays out food in tins.</l>
                        <l>Out of the window perilously spread</l>
                        <l>Her drying combinations touched by the sun’s last rays,</l>
                        <l>On the divan are piled (at night her bed)</l>
                        <l>Stockings, slippers, camisoles, and stays.</l>
                        <l>I Tiresias, old man with wrinkled dugs</l>
                        <l>Perceived the scene, and foretold the rest—</l>
                        <l>I too awaited the expected guest.</l>
                        <l>He, the young man carbuncular, arrives,</l>
                        <l>A small house agent’s clerk, with one bold stare,</l>
                        <l>One of the low on whom assurance sits</l>
                        <l>As a silk hat on a Bradford millionaire.</l>
                        <l>The time is now propitious, as he guesses,</l>
                        <l>The meal is ended, she is bored and tired,</l>
                        <l>Endeavours to engage her in caresses</l>
                        <l>Which still are unreproved, if undesired.</l>
                        <l>Flushed and decided, he assaults at once;</l>
                        <l>Exploring hands encounter no defence;</l>
                        <l>His vanity requires no response,</l>
                        <l>And makes a welcome of indifference.</l>
                        <l>(And I Tiresias have foresuffered all</l>
                        <l>Enacted on this same divan or bed;</l>
                        <l>I who have sat by Thebes below the wall</l>
                        <l>And walked among the lowest of the dead.)</l>
                        <l>Bestows one final patronising kiss,</l>
                        <l>And gropes his way, finding the stairs unlit . . .</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>She turns and looks a moment in the glass,</l>
                        <l>Hardly aware of her departed lover;</l>
                        <l>Her brain allows one half-formed thought to pass:</l>
                        <l>'Well now that’s done: and I’m glad it’s over.’</l>
                        <l>When lovely woman stoops to folly and</l>
                        <l>Paces about her room again, alone,</l>
                        <l>She smooths her hair with automatic hand,</l>
                        <l>And puts a record on the gramophone.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘This music crept by me upon the waters’</l>
                        <l>And along the Strand, up Queen Victoria Street.</l>
                        <l>O City city, I can sometimes hear</l>
                        <l>Beside a public bar in Lower Thames Street,</l>
                        <l>The pleasant whining of a mandoline</l>
                        <l>And a clatter and a chatter from within</l>
                        <l>Where fishmen lounge at noon: where the walls</l>
                        <l>Of Magnus Martyr hold</l>
                        <l>Inexplicable splendour of Ionian white and gold.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>The river sweats</l>
                        <l>Oil and tar</l>
                        <l>The barges drift</l>
                        <l>With the turning tide</l>
                        <l>Red sails</l>
                        <l>Wide</l>
                        <l>To leeward, swing on the heavy spar.</l>
                        <l>The barges wash</l>
                        <l>Drifting logs</l>
                        <l>Down Greenwich reach</l>
                        <l>Past the Isle of Dogs.</l>
                        <l>Weialala leia</l>
                        <l>Wallala leialala</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Elizabeth and Leicester</l>
                        <l>Beating oars</l>
                        <l>The stern was formed</l>
                        <l>A gilded shell</l>
                        <l>Red and gold</l>
                        <l>The brisk swell</l>
                        <l>Rippled both shores</l>
                        <l>Southwest wind</l>
                        <l>Carried down stream</l>
                        <l>The peal of bells</l>
                        <l>White towers</l>
                        <l>Weialala leia</l>
                        <l>Wallala leialala</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘Trams and dusty trees.</l>
                        <l>Highbury bore me. Richmond and Kew</l>
                        <l>Undid me. By Richmond I raised my knees</l>
                        <l>Supine on the floor of a narrow canoe.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘My feet are at Moorgate, and my heart</l>
                        <l>Under my feet. After the event</l>
                        <l>He wept. He promised a ‘new start.’</l>
                        <l>I made no comment. What should I resent?’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>‘On Margate Sands.</l>
                        <l>I can connect</l>
                        <l>Nothing with nothing.</l>
                        <l>The broken fingernails of dirty hands.</l>
                        <l>My people humble people who expect</l>
                        <l>Nothing.’</l>
                        <l>la la</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>To Carthage then I came</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Burning burning burning burning</l>
                        <l>O Lord Thou pluckest me out</l>
                        <l>O Lord Thou pluckest</l>
                        <l>burning</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="4">
                    <head>Death by Water</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Phlebas the Phoenician, a fortnight dead,</l>
                        <l>Forgot the cry of gulls, and the deep sea swell</l>
                        <l>And the profit and loss.</l>
                        <l>A current under sea</l>
                        <l>Picked his bones in whispers. As he rose and fell</l>
                        <l>He passed the stages of his age and youth</l>
                        <l>Entering the whirlpool.</l>
                        <l>Gentile or Jew</l>
                        <l>O you who turn the wheel and look to windward,</l>
                        <l>Consider Phlebas, who was once handsome and tall as you.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="5">
                    <head>What the Thunder Said</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>After the torchlight red on sweaty faces</l>
                        <l>After the frosty silence in the gardens</l>
                        <l>After the agony in stony places</l>
                        <l>The shouting and the crying</l>
                        <l>Prison and palace and reverberation</l>
                        <l>Of thunder of spring over distant mountains</l>
                        <l>He who was living is now dead</l>
                        <l>We who were living are now dying</l>
                        <l>With a little patience</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Here is no water but only rock</l>
                        <l>Rock and no water and the sandy road</l>
                        <l>The road winding above among the mountains</l>
                        <l>Which are mountains of rock without water</l>
                        <l>If there were water we should stop and drink</l>
                        <l>Amongst the rock one cannot stop or think</l>
                        <l>Sweat is dry and feet are in the sand</l>
                        <l>If there were only water amongst the rock</l>
                        <l>Dead mountain mouth of carious teeth that cannot spit</l>
                        <l>Here one can neither stand nor lie nor sit</l>
                        <l>There is not even silence in the mountains</l>
                        <l>But dry sterile thunder without rain</l>
                        <l>There is not even solitude in the mountains</l>
                        <l>But red sullen faces sneer and snarl</l>
                        <l>From doors of mudcracked houses</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>If there were water</l>
                        <l>And no rock</l>
                        <l>If there were rock</l>
                        <l>And also water</l>
                        <l>And water</l>
                        <l>A spring</l>
                        <l>A pool among the rock</l>
                        <l>If there were the sound of water only</l>
                        <l>Not the cicada</l>
                        <l>And dry grass singing</l>
                        <l>But sound of water over a rock</l>
                        <l>Where the hermit-thrush sings in the pine trees</l>
                        <l>Drip drop drip drop drop drop drop</l>
                        <l>But there is no water</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Who is the third who walks always beside you?</l>
                        <l>When I count, there are only you and I together</l>
                        <l>But when I look ahead up the white road</l>
                        <l>There is always another one walking beside you</l>
                        <l>Gliding wrapt in a brown mantle, hooded</l>
                        <l>I do not know whether a man or a woman</l>
                        <l>—But who is that on the other side of you?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>What is that sound high in the air</l>
                        <l>Murmur of maternal lamentation</l>
                        <l>Who are those hooded hordes swarming</l>
                        <l>Over endless plains, stumbling in cracked earth</l>
                        <l>Ringed by the flat horizon only</l>
                        <l>What is the city over the mountains</l>
                        <l>Cracks and reforms and bursts in the violet air</l>
                        <l>Falling towers</l>
                        <l>Jerusalem Athens Alexandria</l>
                        <l>Vienna London</l>
                        <l>Unreal</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>A woman drew her long black hair out tight</l>
                        <l>And fiddled whisper music on those strings</l>
                        <l>And bats with baby faces in the violet light</l>
                        <l>Whistled, and beat their wings</l>
                        <l>And crawled head downward down a blackened wall</l>
                        <l>And upside down in air were towers</l>
                        <l>Tolling reminiscent bells, that kept the hours</l>
                        <l>And voices singing out of empty cisterns and exhausted wells.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>In this decayed hole among the mountains</l>
                        <l>In the faint moonlight, the grass is singing</l>
                        <l>Over the tumbled graves, about the chapel</l>
                        <l>There is the empty chapel, only the wind’s home.</l>
                        <l>It has no windows, and the door swings,</l>
                        <l>Dry bones can harm no one.</l>
                        <l>Only a cock stood on the rooftree</l>
                        <l>Co co rico co co rico</l>
                        <l>In a flash of lightning. Then a damp gust</l>
                        <l>Bringing rain</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Ganga was sunken, and the limp leaves</l>
                        <l>Waited for rain, while the black clouds</l>
                        <l>Gathered far distant, over Himavant.</l>
                        <l>The jungle crouched, humped in silence.</l>
                        <l>Then spoke the thunder</l>
                        <l>DA</l>
                        <l>Datta: what have we given?</l>
                        <l>My friend, blood shaking my heart</l>
                        <l>The awful daring of a moment’s surrender</l>
                        <l>Which an age of prudence can never retract</l>
                        <l>By this, and this only, we have existed</l>
                        <l>Which is not to be found in our obituaries</l>
                        <l>Or in memories draped by the beneficent spider</l>
                        <l>Or under seals broken by the lean solicitor</l>
                        <l>In our empty rooms</l>
                        <l>DA</l>
                        <l>Dayadhvam: I have heard the key</l>
                        <l>Turn in the door once and turn once only</l>
                        <l>We think of the key, each in his prison</l>
                        <l>Thinking of the key, each confirms a prison</l>
                        <l>Only at nightfall, aethereal rumours</l>
                        <l>Revive for a moment a broken Coriolanus</l>
                        <l>DA</l>
                        <l>Damyata: The boat responded</l>
                        <l>Gaily, to the hand expert with sail and oar</l>
                        <l>The sea was calm, your heart would have responded</l>
                        <l>Gaily, when invited, beating obedient</l>
                        <l>To controlling hands</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>I sat upon the shore</l>
                        <l>Fishing, with the arid plain behind me</l>
                        <l>Shall I at least set my lands in order?</l>
                        <l>London Bridge is falling down falling down falling down</l>
                        <l>Poi s’ascose nel foco che gli affina</l>
                        <l>Quando fiam uti chelidon—O swallow swallow</l>
                        <l>Le Prince d’Aquitaine à la tour abolie</l>
                        <l>These fragments I have shored against my ruins</l>
                        <l>Why then Ile fit you. Hieronymo’s mad againe.</l>
                        <l>Datta. Dayadhvam. Damyata.</l>
                        <l>Shantih shantih shantih</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
