<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Waste Land</title>
                <author>T.S. Eliot</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1922</date>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">
                <head>The Waste Land</head>
                <div type="section" n="1">
                    <head>The Burial of the Dead</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>April is the cruellest month, breeding</l>
                        <l>Lilacs out of the dead land, mixing</l>
                        <l>Memory and desire, stirring</l>
                        <l>Dull roots with spring rain.</l>
                        <l>Winter kept us warm, covering</l>
                        <l>Earth in forgetful snow, feeding</l>
                        <l>A little life with dried tubers.</l>
                        <l>Summer surprised us, coming over the Starnbergersee</l>
                        <l>With a shower of rain; we stopped in the colonnade,</l>
                        <l>And went on in sunlight, into the Hofgarten,</l>
                        <l>And drank coffee, and talked for an hour.</l>
                        <l>Bin gar keine Russin, stamm’ aus Litauen, echt deutsch.</l>
                        <l>And when we were children, staying at the archduke’s,</l>
                        <l>My cousin’s, he took me out on a sled,</l>
                        <l>And I was frightened. He said, Marie,</l>
                        <l>Marie, hold on tight. And down we went.</l>
                        <l>In the mountains, there you feel free.</l>
                        <l>I read, much of the night, and go south in the winter.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>What are the roots that clutch, what branches grow</l>
                        <l>Out of this stony rubbish? Son of man,</l>
                        <l>You cannot say, or guess, for you know only</l>
                        <l>A heap of broken images, where the sun beats,</l>
                        <l>And the dead tree gives no shelter, the cricket no relief,</l>
                        <l>And the dry stone no sound of water. Only</l>
                        <l>There is shadow under this red rock,</l>
                        <l>(Come in under the shadow of this red rock),</l>
                        <l>And I will show you something different from either</l>
                        <l>Your shadow at morning striding behind you</l>
                        <l>Or your shadow at evening rising to meet you;</l>
                        <l>I will show you fear in a handful of dust.</l>
                        <l>Frisch weht der Wind</l>
                        <l>Der Heimat zu</l>
                        <l>Mein Irisch Kind,</l>
                        <l>Wo weilest du?</l>
                        <l>‘You gave me hyacinths first a year ago;</l>
                        <l>‘They called me the hyacinth girl.’</l>
                        <l>—Yet when we came back, late, from the Hyacinth garden,</l>
                        <l>Your arms full, and your hair wet, I could not</l>
                        <l>Speak, and my eyes failed, I was neither</l>
                        <l>Living nor dead, and I knew nothing,</l>
                        <l>Looking into the heart of light, the silence.</l>
                        <l>Oed’ und leer das Meer.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Madame Sosostris, famous clairvoyante,</l>
                        <l>Had a bad cold, nevertheless</l>
                        <l>Is known to be the wisest woman in Europe,</l>
                        <l>With a wicked pack of cards. Here, said she,</l>
                        <l>Is your card, the drowned Phoenician Sailor,</l>
                        <l>(Those are pearls that were his eyes. Look!)</l>
                        <l>Here is Belladonna, the Lady of the Rocks,</l>
                        <l>The lady of situations.</l>
                        <l>Here is the man with three staves, and here the Wheel,</l>
                        <l>And here is the one-eyed merchant, and this card,</l>
                        <l>Which is blank, is something he carries on his back,</l>
                        <l>Which I am forbidden to see. I do not find</l>
                        <l>The Hanged Man. Fear death by water.</l>
                        <l>I see crowds of people, walking round in a ring.</l>
                        <l>Thank you. If you see dear Mrs. Equitone,</l>
                        <l>Tell her I bring the horoscope myself:</l>
                        <l>One must be so careful these days.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Unreal City,</l>
                        <l>Under the brown fog of a winter dawn,</l>
                        <l>A crowd flowed over London Bridge, so many,</l>
                        <l>I had not thought death had undone so many.</l>
                        <l>Sighs, short and infrequent, were exhaled,</l>
                        <l>And each man fixed his eyes before his feet.</l>
                        <l>Flowed up the hill and down King William Street,</l>
                        <l>To where Saint Mary Woolnoth kept the hours</l>
                        <l>With a dead sound on the final stroke of nine.</l>
                        <l>There I saw one I knew, and stopped him, crying: ‘Stetson!</l>
                        <l>‘You who were with me in the ships at Mylae!</l>
                        <l>‘That corpse you planted last year in your garden,</l>
                        <l>‘Has it begun to sprout? Will it bloom this year?</l>
                        <l>‘Or has the sudden frost disturbed its bed?</l>
                        <l>‘Oh keep the Dog far hence, that’s friend to men,</l>
                        <l>‘Or with his nails he’ll dig it up again!</l>
                        <l>‘You! hypocrite lecteur!—mon semblable,—mon frère!”</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="2">
                    <head>A Game of Chess</head>
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>The Chair she sat in, like a burnished throne,</l>
                        <l>Glowed on the marble, where the glass</l>
                        <l>Held up by standards wrought with gold</l>
                        <l>From sitting on the stove, he could smell the hot</l>
                    </lg>
                    <!-- Additional stanzas and lines here -->
                </div>
                <!-- Additional sections here -->
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
